{
  "reference_number": "2439",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Without a definite commitment change will be too difficult."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Having already exceeded all previous targets and with continued high world population growth it is now necessary to set unilateral\n and ambitious targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "New Zealand should become a world leader with or without input from other countries."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "There will be significant pressure from industry and other interest groups which will make focussed determination essential."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Provided it is not possible to use this as a mechanism for not achieving the original targets. (Revisionist equivocation)"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "As has so far consistently been the case, this otherwise allows for subsequent governments to not meet previously agreed targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The most likely reason for wanting to do this would be to allow for economic imperatives at the expense of the environment. New\n\n thinking and policy must be developed."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Subject to new scientific understanding and international cooperation."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Successive government must be committed to continuity."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The overall and continued health of the ecosystem including a fully integrated human species."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It is vital to have a strong monitoring agency."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The NZ ETS must evolve as our understanding of environmental imperatives deepens."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "With care taken to protect impartiality and avoid the influence of industrial or special interest groups. [Pharmacutical and agricultural\nmultinationals and other nations through trade agreements etc]"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Given the current starting point and likely levels of progress it is essential that it does."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Provided those organisations cannot influence policy."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Having spent my 20s living in Kenya where the average energy consumption was 0.5 barrels of oil per year (energy equivalent) and\n\nmy 30s in California where people were 90 times as consumptive I am aware of just how far from a sustainable base line we are. As an\nOcean Engineer and Marine Warranty Surveyor I spent the 90s overseeing the installation of very large offshore oil and gas facilities\nincluding Hibernia and those of the North Dome field offshore Qatar. I moved to New Zealand looking for a more balanced and\n\nsustainable lifestyle for myself and my family. But, apart from the low ratio of people to the environment have not found it here. New\nZealand is in a unique position of being able to use its low population and isolated ecosystem to lead the world in alternative\n\nsustainable living. Whether it chooses to do so remains to be seen. However, I believe like the rest of the world it will soon have little\nchoice."
    }
  ]
}
